Guide to the Papers of the Cavendish-Talbot Family Folger MS X.d.428 (1-203)
Folger Shakespeare Library
- Wentworth family papers, 1627-1705; Series 2; X.d.428 (148-169)
  - Correspondence, 2.1
    - Letter from William Wentworth, Earl of Strafford, Rouen, to Sir George Wentworth of Woolley, and Thomas Wentworth, Esq., 1648 October 15; X.d.428 (160)
      Asks his kinsmen to further his business concerning his estate and trust. He has written to his Uncle Clare to get passes for the Earl of Strafford's sisters to come out of England, and hopes that his uncle and aunt will come with them, but if in doing so or in staying at Woodhouse they "find any preuidice," he desires that his sisters entreat "My Lady" to be with them there. He has heard since that his uncle intends not to go away, of which he is glad. His sister Anne will acquaint them what money must be prepared.
      Thomas Wentworth, Esq., later Sir Thomas Wentworth, bart., of Bretton.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/zf7r6e
    - Letter from William Wentworth, London, to Sir Matthew Wentworth, 2nd bart., Dublin, 1675/6 January; X.d.428 (161)
      Asks him to make his (William's) children his heirs, to keep the estate in the Wentworth name. The funeral was magnificent, costing £1200 (possibly Sir Thomas Wentworth's, d. 1675).
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/194b19
    - Letter from John Whitehead, London, to Sir Matthew Wentworth, 2nd bart., 1675/6 March 14; X.d.428 (162)
      Suggests a marriage between Sir Matthew's son and one of Whitehead's nieces. Describes the various nieces and their fortunes. He has taken his wife and daughter to London, so "that they may see this Famous Citty."
      Seal intact (slightly damaged).
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/00nfw7
    - Warrant for arrest from West Riding, Yorkshire, to the constable of Attercliffe, all other constables in the West Riding, and their deputies, 1705 May 18; X.d.428 (167)
      Warrant to arrest anyone whose lands are worth less than £100 per annum found with the means for destroying game. Means of destruction include guns, bows, greyhounds, ferrets, dogs.
      Signed: Thomas Wentworth, at W[entworth] Woodhouse [Yorkshire]. Seal intact.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/jn643q
    - Letter from unknown correspondent from the Inner Temple to Sir Thomas Wentworth, bart., Bretton, 1665 April 7; X.d.428 (168)
      Gives news of the arrival of the French ambassador, who will remain incognito until his large retinue comes, and of the navy's preparations during the Second Dutch War. Also, describes a comet.
      On address leaf: "post paid -3d:" "fferrybrigg" (i.e. Ferrybridge, West Yorkshire), stamped with date "Ap 8." Seal intact (black). Letter damaged.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/qpqu38
  - Other documents, 2.2
    - Order for the collection of the second subsidy, addressed to the high constables within the wapentake of Osgodcrosse and Staincross, West Riding, Yorkshire, 1624 October 5; X.d.428 (163)
      And in particular to Aymer Rich (i.e. Eymer Ryche) at Bulhouse (Bethane's Baronetage V, 451).Written from Wakefield, West Yorkshire. Signed by Sir Thomas Wentworth, later Earl of Strafford, as custos rotulorum, Sir Richard Beaumont, and another Thomas Wentworth.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/8yi51e
    - Acquittance from West Riding, Yorkshire, to Francis Popeley of Gomersal, 1630 September 23; X.d.428 (164)
      Acquittance for the discharge of £10 in composition money paid for not attending and receiving the order of knighthood at the king's coronation.
      Signed: Wentworth, [Sir Thomas, later 1st earl of Strafford].
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/h5mh90
    - Acquittance from West Riding, Yorkshire, to Miles Dodson of Kirkby Overblow, 1630 September 25; X.d.428 (165)
      Acquittance for the discharge of £15 in composition money paid for not attending and receiving the order of knighthood at the king's coronation. Signed: Wentworth, (Sir Thomas, later 1st earl of Strafford).
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/iqzjve
    - Order to all officers and soldiers under John Lambert's command, Pontefract, Yorkshire, 1648 December 11; X.d.428 (155)
      They are not to seize the horses or goods of Thomas Wentworth of Bretton, Yorkshire, Esq., later Sir Thomas Wentworth, bart. A note in another hand states: "Remember to search for Bradshawe will Swinburne and Payler."
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/i3n7h2
    - Account of the expenses incurred in the business of William Wentworth, Earl of Strafford, 1651 July 29-1651 October 16; X.d.428 (169)
      Touching the forfeited and settled estate. Signed: William Taylor. Also, an incomplete rough draft of a bond between John Haigh the elder and John Haigh the younger, undated.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/5z2t29
    - Order addressed to the assessors of the town of Thurlston in the wapentake of Staincross, West Riding, Yorkshire, 1667/8 January 25; X.d.428 (166)
      Written from Barnsley, South Yorkshire. By act of Parliament, Commissioners are to collect one month's assessment to the king and pay it to the head collector, who adds a note overleaf.
      Signed: T. Wentworth and J. Wentworth. Two seals, one intact.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/65v8rm
    - Legal opinion of Thomas Gunter, 1676 November 18; X.d.428 (152)
      Advises on the action to be taken by Lady Wentworth, concerning the publication of anonymous scurrilous verses against her late husband, Sir Thomas Wentworth, bart. (d. December 5, 1675) which had been sent to his brother, Sir Matthew Wentworth, 2nd bart.
      http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/2xge0u
- Slingsby family letters, 1586-1634; Series 3; X.d.428 (170-194)
  - Letter from Peter Benson, Knaresborough (i.e. Knar), Yorkshire, to Sir Francis Trappes-Byrnand., 1620 December 31; X.d.428 (170)
    Asks that he arbitrate between himself and Sir Henry Slingsby.
    See also X.d.428 (188, 189).
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/8zkn8b
  - Letter from William Byrnand, Hawnby, Yorkshire, to Mr. Francis Slingsby, ca. 1630 April 12; X.d.428 (171)
    He has received the surrender from Ralph Mawtus and forwards it to Francis, his uncle.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/p4920w
  - Letter from Sir Charles Cavendish, Welbeck, Nottinghamshire, to Sir Henry Slingsby at Red House (i.e. Redhouse), Yorkshire, 1633 August 13; X.d.428 (172)
    Has asked Sir Ferdinando Fairfax to hear and determine the matter concerning the arrearages of tithe due to him (Sir Charles).
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/z46fgj
  - Letter from Baron Thomas, Howsham (i.e. Howsom), Yorkshire, to Sir Henry Slingsby, 1627 November 27; X.d.428 (173)
    Mentions his (Fairfax's) new office, as sheriff for Yorkshire. The bailwick of Claro has already been given to Sir Henry Goodwick (or Goodricke) and Sir Peter Middleton of Stockeld, (kinsman to Thomas Wentworth); if Slingsby had asked sooner, he would have granted the bailwick to him.
    Baron Thomas Fairfax was later the Viscount Fairfax of Elmley, in the Irish peerage.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/tkg9rz
  - Letter from Sir John Gibson to Sir Henry Slingsby, 1631? January 30; X.d.428 (174)
    Sir John Bingley will bring Captain Skipwith to Sir A[rthur] Ingram's. The new lord chief baron of the Exchequer (Sir Humphrey Davenport) "goes rowndly to worke," fining the sheriffs for their "negligent returns about knightinge." Fears that Master H. Stapleton will be fined. Hopes to attend him soon in Yorkshire.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/p5wk99
  - Letter from John Hutchinson, York, to Sir Henry Slingsby?, 1632 May 7; X.d.428 (175)
    He has learned from a gentleman of Lord Fairfax's that his son is prisoner, because of a "trifling Debt," in the Marshalsea at London, where "the Company may easily make a young man worse addicted." Desires Slingsby to pay the money, thought it be £5, to release him, for which he will be reimbursed. Letter unaddressed, assumed to be to Sir Henry Slingsby.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/kz5ndp
  - Letter from Sir George Marwood, bart., London, to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, 1630 November 12; X.d.428 (176)
    Informs his [grand]father-in-law of certain business matters in London, including Widow Darnton's rent, a letter to John Todd, a letter served to the Duchess of Lennox, and a privy seal served to "one of the Defendants." Sir William Fitch is not in town, Sir William Slingsby is at Richmond but returns to London tomorrow, Master Dymock promises an answer, and his (Marwood's) brother Slingsby is with Master Vincent.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/i4x857
  - Letter from Christopher Mather to Francis Slingsby, 1586 December 20 or 28; X.d.428 (177)
    Written on St. Thomas' eve. Gives the date on which the commissioners will meet. Hopes Master Robert Oglethorpe will accept his (Mather's) bond.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/6jv69b
  - Letter from Sir Thomas Metcalfe, Kirby Hall, Yorkshire, to Sir Henry Slingsby, at Master Park's house in Fetter Lane, London, 1620/1 January 26; X.d.428 (178)
    Informs his father-in-law of the status of his court case against his tenant, one Robinson of Thorneton, and asks for his assistance in procuring the orders entered for the discharge of Clotherom, in order for Metcalfe to relieve himself and his family. Mentions Baron Denham, Justice Chamberlain, Lord Montgomery, Lord Haddington, and James I in connection with the case. His cousin, Thomas Musgrave, will fully inform Slingsby about the grant for the recognizance.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/7m38m8
  - Letter from Henry Percy, Earl of Northumberland, to Sir Henry Slingsby, 1613 July 26; X.d.428 (179)
    Asks his cousin to be a member of the commission which is to hold courts of survey in each of his manors.
    Seal intact, (reproduced in Smith, Without Touch of Dishonour, opposite p. 45).
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/sqpggb
  - Letter from Robert Norton to Sir Henry Slingsby, at Master Park's house in Fetter Lane, London., 1632 November 29; X.d.428 (180)
    On estate matters at Red House, Yorkshire; discusses a shortage of capons and hens and how to provide better provisions for his young master for this Christmas.
    Date: endorsed as 1632, signed as 1623.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/880zm5
  - Letter from Robert Norton to Sir Henry Slingsby, at Master Park's house on Fetter Lane, London, 1632/3 January 3; X.d.428 (181)
    Concerning management of his woods, orchards, and hedges at Red House.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/17p146
  - Letter from Phanuell (i.e. Phatuel) Otby, Staveley, Yorkshire, to Sir Henry Slingsby, vice-president of the Council of the North, 1627 December 10; X.d.428 (182)
    About the election of burgesses to the next Parliament. Otby's son-in-law has been informed concerning Sir Henry's request. He will do his best. Asks Sir Henry to assist the bearer of the letter in his suit. (Otby, rector of Staveley, Yorkshire, had been tutor to Sir Henry's sons Henry and Thomas).
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/89m6xx
  - Letter from Francis? Slingsby, London, to Sir Robert Cecil, 1597 July 12; X.d.428 (183)
    Expresses gratitude to Cecil for presenting him to the queen in the garden at Greenwich, who gave him her hand to kiss and thanked him for his service. Asks him to be one of the hearers of his petition to the queen.
    Sir Robert Cecil, later Earl of Salisbury.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/e9v8xp
  - Letter from Guilford Slingsby, London, to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, Yorkshire, 1631 August 28; X.d.428 (184)
    Apologizes to his uncle for a letter of his which never arrived at Red House. Reports that Sir Henry's letter to Master Wansforth was well-received. Wansforth has assured Guilford that he will move Lord Cottington again, either by himself or jointly with Sir Roger Palmer.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/n5g619
  - Letter from Guilford Slingsby, Dublin Castle, to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, Yorkshire, 1634 June 22; X.d.428 (185)
    Asks his uncle if there is any possibility of recovering his horse from his cousin and selling it, since he has not received any money out of England since coming to Ireland. "My lord" has employed him for the Vice-Admiralty of Munster and recommended him to be chosen a burgess in the present Parliament. Refers to the troubles between his uncle Sir Francis and his wife, and the "misfortune concerninge there sonne," which "was the occasion, (as I enterpret of it) of his late goinge to see her to comforte her."
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/4jg83m
  - Letter from Sir Robert Slingsby, bart., to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, Yorkshire, 1631 September 17; X.d.428 (186)
    Informs his uncle that he is still without employment; the cardinal is coming by land; he has heard no more of Sir Kenelm Digby's voyage. He hopes for employment soon, however, since the king is building ships. He has been learning Spanish, so that "if any Embasador should be sent thither, I might be fitt to attend him."
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/5f29i2
  - Letter from Sir William Slingsby, the Strand, London, to Sir Henry Slingsby, York, 1634 July 6; X.d.428 (187)
    He has sent his tomb "packt vpp in two great sugar-Chestes," and needs his brother's help in transporting it from Hull to the chapel at Knaresborough, where their father's tomb lies. Mentions the European travels of his nephew Francis, his dispute with the archbishop of York concerning a lease, and Sir Walter Bethel's (Henry's son-in-law) trip to the Forest of Dean with Henry Rich, Earl of Holland.
    Seal intact, (reproduced in Smith, Without Touch of Dishonour, facing p. 45; photograph of tomb, designed by Epiphanius Evesham, facing p. 61)
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/7yh54w
  - Letter from Sir Francis Trappes-Byrnand to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, 1620 September 13; X.d.428 (188)
    Apologizes to his cousin for not writing, but "sorrow is an ill secretary." Upon the serving of the king's letter yesterday, he wrote to Peter Benson that he could say nothing, and if nothing but his oath will satisfy Benson, Benson must procure a commission. Requests that Sir Henry return Peter Benson's letter and asks him how to "prevent contempt for I cannot ryde to yorke." He has been told that Anthony Craven had not bought Stavely nor was it sold.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/o8f23o
  - Letter from Sir Francis Trappes-Byrnand to Sir Henry Slingsby, Red House, 1620 September 14; X.d.428 (189)
    He cannot write much because he has "such a payne in my head." Henry Benson has brought him a letter, dated April 1612, from Sir Francis to his father Peter Benson, in which Sir Francis declared Sir Henry's consent to "certayn thinges agreed to betweene your self and him." Henry Benson would not show him the letter until Sir Francis promised to return it to him undefaced, and mentioned another incriminating letter in Sir Henry's hand to Sir Francis. This requires consideration, and he wishes that they might all speak together.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/5y1d6m
  - Letter from Christopher Wade to Sir Henry Slingsby, 1626 December 20; X.d.428 (190)
    Discusses estate matters, such as bonds, the sowing of beans, Sherriff Hodgson, barley, the building of a stone wall, woodcutting.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/7q5s9k
  - Letter from Thomas Wardropp, mayor of Ripon, Ripon, to Sir Henry Slingsby, York, ca. 1630? December 15; X.d.428 (191)
    Discusses particulars of the raising of the aid due to the king for the knighting of his son (i.e. Prince Charles).
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/wywm07
  - Letter from Edward Wilson, London, to Sir Henry Slingsby?, 1623 December 9; X.d.428 (192)
    Discusses estate matters. Informs him that Master John Pascoll has begun to plow the forty acres of marshland "which is in Controversie" between Sir Henry and Pascoll, despite Wilson's having forbidden him to do so. Wilson is now so troubled by Master Pascoll and one Master Porter that they will not allow him passage "either to Market or mill." The chimney has been pulled down and a new brick one built for £12.
    Endorsed: "Edwarde Willson my Tennant at 'Stewe marris'" (i.e. Stow Maries, Essex). Hand of endorsement similar to that in letters to Sir Henry Slingsby.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/w61722
  - Letter from Samuel Wortley, Swinton, Yorkshire, to Thomas Hall at Wightwizzle (i.e. Wigtwisell), Yorkshire, 1628 October 27; X.d.428 (193)
    Hall's kinsmen seek money owed to them from Hall, which Wortley urges him to pay, "for sutes is good for nobody."
    See Place-Names of the West Riding of Yorkshire for more information on Wightwizzle.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/5x8e4s
  - Letter from William Wycliffe, Newcastle, to Francis Slingsby, Scriven, Yorkshire, 1586 December 11; X.d.428 (194)
    Asks him to help further the collection of the fines in Northumberland. He understands Slingsby has received the rents from the Earl of Cumberland and Lady Lennox.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/cd2jbx
- Sir Humphrey Style letter, ca. 1629; Series 4; X.d.428 (195)
  - Letter from Sir Humphrey Style, bart., M. de Soubise's house near Salisbury, to Lady Elizabeth Style, Aldersgate Street, London, 1632/3? February 16; X.d.428 (195)
    There is no news "but of horses and dogs." Instructs his wife to go to Lady Prescott's (Prescots) house on Saturday, March 2, where she should stay until he comes to fetch her when the assizes are ended. Details concerning servants, an order to the haberdasher, and the outfitting of horses and riders, that "wee maye make the better showe."
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/1j4j1n
- Gower family letters, 1636-1658; Series 5; X.d.428 (196-200)
  - Letter from Stanley and Sarah Gower, Brampton Bryan, Herefordshire, to John and Mary Stainforth at Darnall, Yorkshire, 1636 April 5; X.d.428 (196)
    A conventional letter of love and gratitude to their son and daughter, beginning "Children are the liuing images of theyr parents." This and the following letters speak of his (Gower's) indebtedness to Stainforth. Mention of his wife's godson and his goddaughter (the children of the Stainforth's) and of Gower's patron, Sir Robert Harley.
    Signed also by Sarah. Seal intact.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/u13hm9
  - Letter from Stanley Gower to John Stainforth, 1636 December 5; X.d.428 (197)
    Repeats his indebtedness to Stainforth, promising to repay him soon. Calculations of sums of money on overleaf. Presumably to John Stainforth.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/sgl27v
  - Letter from Stanley and Sarah Gower, Brampton Bryan, Herefordshire, to John or Mary Stainforth, Darnall, Yorkshire, 1638 March 29; X.d.428 (198)
    Repeated assurances of repaying the debt, beginning, "Pitty the condition of your poore but louing parents, that are not able to lay vp for yow, but yow for them." Stanley has sent his goddaughter "a little psalme booke, which I hope by this tyme shee can make vse of," and Sarah has sent her godson an "AEols blast out of a payre of bellows."
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/0l65hv
  - Letter from Stanley and Sarah Gower to John Stainforth, Darnall, Yorkshire, 1647 April 1; X.d.428 (199)
    Answers his request for help in placing his (John's) daughter here. "Our plundered condition maks vs keepe but one mayd," but John's daughter's ability in reading, writing, sewing, and starching "will render hir acceptable in very good places." They expect the arrival of the Scottish Commissioners, "then both kingdoms send propositions to the King." Some members of the House of Commons have ordered Sir Thomas Fairfax to send soldiers into Ireland: the Presbyterian party obeys, the Independents demur and prepare a mutinous petition.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/3b93n3
  - Letter from Stanley and Sarah Gower, Brampton Bryan, Herefordshire, to John Stainforth, Darnall, Yorkshire, 1658 June 14; X.d.428 (200)
    They will continue to try and obtain Stainforth-'s discharge through the good offices of his patron, Sir Edward Harley. Wishes he was lord Arundel when his son traveled with him to Shrewsbury, so that he could have commanded him to go to Brampton where Gower would have been able to pay him, and entertain him. Laments "that nonpayment of our debt."
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/yowt0o
- Miscellaneous documents, 1500-1548; Series 6; X.d.428 (201-203)
  - Copy of memorandum of a lease for 5 years to Master Pelle, 1333, ca. 1500; X.d.428 (201)
    For land in Blackbowrow Hawse (i.e. Blackborough House, probably in Kentisbeare, Devon). Dated: 7 Edward III. Paper copy.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/inofs4
  - Copy of will of Thomas Barbur of Hope, Staffordshire, August 3, 1529, 16th century; X.d.428 (202)
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/4v3uf5
  - Copy of Acknowledgement of receipt from Charles Bromehead, of Clifton, Nottinghamshire to Alice White, June 25, 1548, 16th century; X.d.428 (203)
    Acknowledgement of the receipt of £5, 13 shillings, 4 pence from Alice White (Whyett, Whyeghtt), sometime wife of the late John Bromehead of Burwell Mary, Cambridgeshire, bequeathed him in Bromehead's will.
    http://luna.folger.edu/luna/servlet/s/d8ca02